<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The. vii. shedynges of the blode of Ihesu cryste</title>
            <title>Contemplacyon or medytacyon of the shedynge of the blood of our lorde Jhesu Cryste at seven tymes.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1509</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68262</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14546.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100703</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836533</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836533</idno>
            <idno type="VID">812</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68262)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 812)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 11:20, 81:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The. vii. shedynges of the blode of Ihesu cryste</title>
                  <title>Contemplacyon or medytacyon of the shedynge of the blood of our lorde Jhesu Cryste at seven tymes.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fletestrete at the signe of the sonne, by Wynkyn de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Enprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>The yere of our lorde god. M.ccccc.ix.] [1509]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First known edition (STC 14546) entitled: A contemplacyon or medytacyon of the shedynge of the blood of our lorde Jhesu Cryste at seven tymes.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 14572 on reel 11.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 14572.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reels 11 and 81 (both Cambridge University Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Passion --  Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:812:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:812:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The .vii. ſhedynges of the blode of Iheſu cryſte.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Ieſus nazarenꝰ rexiudeo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>rum</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </head>
                  <figDesc>Jesus on a cross</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:812:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ Here begynneth a contemplacyon or medytacyon of the ſhedynge of the blode of our lorde Iheſu Cryſte at ſeuen tymes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E ought oftentymes to remembre deuoutly many &amp; greuous paynes that our lord Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu cryſt ſuffred for our redempcion / that our loue may be the more feruent to hym. And we ſeynge his grete loue and kyndnes / may for his loue pacyently ſuffre tribulacyons &amp; dyſeaſes in this worlde / leſte we for our vnkyndenes be caſt from his face in to euerlaſtynge payne. ¶ Amonge his gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous paynes he ſhedde his precyous blode for our loue vii. tymes the whiche ſholde often be conſydered of vs. But whan we ſhall conſyder his paynes or whan we ſhall praye / yf we wyll haue comfortable felynge of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocyon in our ſoule. At the begynnynge of our prayer or contemplacyon we muſt withdrawe our mynde and wyttes fro all outwarde thynges &amp; beſynes as moche as we may. And thynke on that thynge that our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>placyon or prayer is of. As yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wylte deuoutly remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre his circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyſyon / thou mayſt thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke as yf thou myght ſe afore the our bleſſyd lorde Iheſus in his chyldhode / that is to ſaye a fayre lytell babe a meke &amp; a ſwete la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me ſo clene / ſoo pure / ſoo pleaſaunt to beholde &amp; loke on his bleſſyd vyſage / ſo amyable his fauourable eyen / ſoo full of grace his Innocent handes &amp; feet / ſo prety &amp; loueſom ſo fayre and whyte very god &amp; man borne of a virgyne pure. And than haue pyte &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſyon in thy herte that ſo fayre &amp; fauourable a babe / ſo ſwete and bleſſyd Inno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cent that neuer dyde amyſſe / ſholde ſuffre ſoo greuous payne as he ſuffred for the / whan his tender fleſſhe was
<pb facs="tcp:812:2"/>cutte with a knyfe made of ſtone whan he was but. viii dayes olde. Take hede how pyteouſly he wepeth in his moders armes for anguyſſhe &amp; payne / and wepe with hym yf thou can. For y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> arte the cauſe of his wepynge / for he ſuffred gyltles ſuche paynes for the loue of the / &amp; ſo whyle the mater is freſſhe in thy mynde / thou mayſt begyn thy deuocyon.</p>
            <p>THe ſeconde tyme that our lorde &amp; ſauyour cryſte Iheſu ſhedde his precyous blode for vs / was in the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>re of Olyuete / where he ſeynge his tedyous and horryble paynes of his bytter paſſyon drawynge nere / for grete anguyſſhe &amp; payne ſwette water &amp; blode. Here mayſt thou thinke as thou ſaweſt hym knelynge on the grounde holdynge vp his holy handes lyftynge vp his face to heuen with the mooſt pyteous chere &amp; rufull coſt tenaunce that thou canſt ymagyne. Thynke as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſawe veryly his eyen ſwollen &amp; reed for wepynge / &amp; al his face chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged with a meruayllous cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenaunce of heuynes. And thynke as thou ſaweſt &amp; herdeſt hym ſobbe wepe &amp; ſyghe full heuyly / &amp; how mournyngly he prayeth to the fader of heuen / how plentefully he wepeth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fader of heuen / how thycke the teeres ranne downe by his che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes / how he wepeth his eyen &amp; face waſſhed with teres / how his body is wete of it / as it were all bathed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and blode and water. Thou mayſt well thynke he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fred greuous payne inwarde / that ſwette outwarde on his body water &amp; blode. And the paynes of his paſſyon were greuous ſyth the thynkynge therof cauſed hym to ſwete blode &amp; water. For the whiche payne deſyre thou as hertely as thou can to wepe with hym / for thou arte the cauſe of his greuous payne. And whyle thou haſte
<pb facs="tcp:812:3"/>this freſſhe in thy mynde faye thy deuocyon.</p>
            <p>THe thyrde tyme our ſauyour ſhedde his <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>cyous blode for vs / was wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to a pyller &amp; with ſcarpe ſcourges was cruelly beten. Here mayſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> thynke as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſawe him veryly afore the naked bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den to a pyller / &amp; how cruelly &amp; fyerſly the curſed tyrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes pyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheth or ſmyteth hym without mercy with whyppes &amp; roddes / ſo that no hole ſkynne is lefte vpon hym. Thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſaweſt the ſtremes of his precyous blode rennyn ge downe on euery ſyde after the greuous and ſmarte laſſhes of the whyppes / &amp; that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſeeſt the bare &amp; naked bones / the fleſſhe rente fro the bones with many &amp; fell ſtrokes of the knotted ſcourges dyed with his precyous blode. Thynke alſo that thou hereſt hym grone / quake and tremble for anguyſſhe and wonderfull payne / how pyteouſly he caſteth his loke towarde heuen / and that with the ſtrokes of the ſcourges a parte of his bleſſyd fleſſhe or a droppe of his precyous blode falleth or drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth on thy face or on thy clothes / this payne ſuffred he for the loue of the / therfore y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ought to haue more pyte on hym. And with as good deuocyon as thou can / lyfte thy herte &amp; mynde to hym / &amp; ſaye thy prayer.</p>
            <p>THe fourth tyme our bleſſyd lorde ſhedde his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blode for our redempcyon / was as he was crowned with a garlond of ſharpe thornes. Here mayſt thou thynke / as yf thou ſeeſt hym ſyttynge afore the his handes bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de behynde hym / &amp; the boyſtous tyrauntes ſettynge a greuous garlonde of ſharpe thornes on his heed / &amp; preſſynge it downe with ſo grete vyolence / that the ſharpe thornes perced in to his brayne. Take hede
<pb facs="tcp:812:3"/>and beholde his rufull and heuy countenaunce / how py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſly he ſhrynketh his necke in to his ſholders for the grete anguyſſhe of that grete &amp; horryble payne / &amp; how pyteouſly he groneth for grefe of that horryble payne / how pyteouſly the ſtremes of blode renneth aboute his heed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to torne in euery ſyde. Beholde his bleſſyd vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſomtyme was ſo pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / ſo gracyous / ſo amya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is now made ſo reed with blode &amp; all dyſfygured w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſorowe &amp; heuynes / his eeres &amp; his noſe be ſtopped with blode. Beholde &amp; ſe how pacyently he that was god and man &amp; is / ſuffred to be ſcornefully mocked with rybau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; caytyues: &amp; his bleſſyd face to be foyled with theyr lothſome ſpyttynge / and all for the loue of man / therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re man ought to haue therof grete compaſſyon.</p>
            <p>THe fyfth tyme our ſauyour ſhedde his precyous blode for vs / was whan his clothes were taken fro him after his ſcourgynge. Here y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſt thynke as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſeeſt hym as afore with a full heuy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenaunce gronyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge pyteouſly with many a depe &amp; profou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſygh comyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his herte rote. And the tyrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes pullynge freſſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of his clothes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> clyued faſt with drye blode to his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre body / for in pullynge away his clothes the ſkynne &amp; the fleſſhe rent fro his body y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cliued ſo faſt to his clothes with drye blode / by the whiche he was all to rente / all to raſſhed / &amp; all to torne &amp; ſtremed all with blode / and ſo he bledde newe agayne. I trowe this payne was more gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous to hym than his ſcourgynge. Remembre how he ſhrynketh trembleth &amp; quaketh &amp; ſtoupeth lowe downe in all his body in pullynge of his clothes for the bytter anguyſſhe of that greuous payne. Beholde how rew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully he is arayed lyke no man but more lyke a thynge
<pb facs="tcp:812:4"/>that were newe ſlayne without ony ſkynne / yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> canſt not remembre the anguyſſhe of this payne / thou mayſt pynche thy fynger or ſome other parte of thy body / that by the felynge of thyn owne lytell payne thou mayſt the better remembre the grete payne that he ſuffred for the whiche thou were cauſe of.</p>
            <p>THe ſyxth tyme that our lord ſhedde his precious blode / was whan his bleſſyd &amp; Innocent ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and fete were nayled to the croſſe. Here mayſt thou thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke as yf thou ſeeſt hym / the fyers cruell tyrauntes &amp; tur mentours of our mercyfull lorde hale &amp; pull his bleſſyd armes / ſome the one and ſome the other / ſo ſore / that it may ſeme to the that thou hereſt his Ioyntes to cracke and the ſenewes to braſte in ſondre. Than mayſt thou thynke that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſeeſt him dryue that is dryuer of the grete nayles in to his holy &amp; ſwete handes &amp; feet / &amp; that thou beholdeſt the dryuer of the nayles &amp; ſeeſt hym w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ony ruthe or pyte ſmyte in euery nayle with many myghty / &amp; that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſeeſt the blode ſpringe out at euery ſtro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke / than ſeeſt our lorde ſhrynke and quake for hydeous payne and ſmarty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of his tender fleſſhe newe cutte at euery ſtroke. This mayſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> thynke fyrſt on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one hande and after on that other &amp; alſo on the feet. Than y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſt beholde with ruthe &amp; compaſſyon how pyteouſly &amp; how greuous &amp; hydeous payne they ſpoyled his clothes / his fleſſhe all to rente and to torne hangeth bledynge on the croſſe / hauynge no thynge as I ſuppoſe to ſuſteyne the weyght of his body ne to reſte hym vpon but the harde nayled fyxed within his tendre fleſſhe / this was to hym a double payne / the whiche were to hym bothe greuous &amp; harde to ſuffre the grete akynges &amp; anguyſſhes bothe
<pb facs="tcp:812:4"/>in his armes &amp; ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des &amp; feet. Another payne of ſore ſmar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge in his handes &amp; feet oppreſſyd harde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the nayles fyxed in the quycke fleſſhe. Bothe this paynes horryble were cauſed by the weyght of his precyous body. Behol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge alſo the ryuers of blode flowynge out of his han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; feet. Thou mayſt thynke alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes quake &amp; tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble for payne / &amp; that for werynes &amp; anguyſſhe of his intollerable payne he ſomtyme ſhaketh his heed rufully and heuely / ſomtyme caſteth it vpon his ryght ſholder / ſomtyme vpon his lefte ſholder / &amp; ſomtyme lyfteth it vp full pyteouſly as a man ſwounynge &amp; halfe deed / leteth it fall downe to his breſte. Than mayſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> beholde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dole full countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his face / how pale it is. And y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſt thynke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> amonge all theſe paynes &amp; ſorowes he lytteth vp his eyen &amp; loketh vpon the in token of loue. As who ſayth I loue the ſo moche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wylfully ſuffre this payne for the / &amp; am redy to ſuffre more yf it be put to me. And that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholdeſt remembre what he hath done for the.</p>
            <p>THe .vii. tyme that our mercyfull ſauyour ſhedde his precyous blode for vs / was whan he hanged on the croſſe &amp; was ſmyten in to the ſyde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſpere. Here mayſt thou thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke as yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſeeſt the body of our mercyfull lorde after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he for our treſpaſſe hath ſuffred pacyently many outrages &amp; excedynge paynes hynge deed vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe all pale &amp; wanne or lyke to be a beeſt newly ſlayne for he ſpared not his owne blode / but gaue it wylfully for our redempcyon. After that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt with pyte &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſyon beholden well how pyteouſly his viſage ſomty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me mooſt beauteous &amp; amyable ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth inclined downe all wanne &amp; pale of colour his precyous body / alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> exce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth all other in beaute &amp; fayrenes hangeth all to rent &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:812:5"/>torne. Thou mayſt beholde how the ſpere re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth thrugh his ſyde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grete vyolence &amp; renneth thrugh his herte / &amp; thou mayſt thynke how y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> herde the ſowne of the cruell ſtroke entrynge in to his ſyde / &amp; that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſeeſt blode &amp; wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was redy to renne haſtely out to waſſhe awaye thy fylth &amp; make the clene / flowed out at the terrible wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of his ſyde / and ranne parte downe on the ſpere &amp; parte downe on his ſyde. O ſwete Iheſu how pacyently how mekely ſuffreſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſo vnkyndly to be entreated / ſo cruelly turmented / ſo rufully arayed for the loue of man. O ten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der &amp; mercyfull lorde that after that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt ſpent thy blo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of thy body to deth / woldeſt after thy deth for the loue of thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſpende all the precyous blode of thy body &amp; herte. After yf pyte &amp; compaſſyon wolde ſuffre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou mayſt loke in at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wounde of his ſyde &amp; beholde how his herte that was free &amp; kynde to the is rennen / torne and ſmyten thrugh with the ſpere. And with deuoute prayer &amp; compaſſyon deſyre that he ſuffre thy loue neuer to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte fro hym / but that thou mayſt be redy for the loue of hym pacyently to ſuffre payne and aduerſyte of this wretched world / for he ſuffred gyltles mekely &amp; pacyent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly moche payne &amp; anguyſſhe for the loue of the. Bycauſe the deuoute memorye of the bytter paſſyon of our ſauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our expelleth temptacion and excyteth many tymes the deuocyon of the true louer of our lorde. Thou mayſte thynke &amp; ymagyn on that our mercyfull redemer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playneth &amp; not without a cauſe / for the grete Iniurye &amp; vnkyndenes of the Iewes / &amp; ſayth to them in this wyſe O ye myn owne / how may ye fynde in your hertes ſoo vncurteyſly to entreate me / ſythen I haue choſen you before other / &amp; brought you fro ſtraunge nacyons and put you in my delectable vyneyarde. I haue create and
<pb facs="tcp:812:5"/>made you lyke vnto my ſelfe / &amp; ye haue laboured to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye me / &amp; haue cauſed me gyltles to be put to ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deth on the croſſe lyke a thefe or a manſleer. I chaſe and preferred you before people of other nacyons / &amp; ye haue done to me grete vilany &amp; made me obieccyon &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſyon of people. And I by many myracles in correccy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your aduerſaryes of Egypte loſed you from capty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uite &amp; brought you out of theyr ſubieccyon. And by fals accuſacyons &amp; excitynge &amp; ſterynge of the people ayenſt me / hath cauſed me without treſpaſſe to be nayled and faſtened to a tree / and gyltles to dye. I mynyſtred to you lyght wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was derke / that ye myght eſcape ſaue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of your aduerſaryes: &amp; ye came ayenſt me with lyght of lanternes ſwerdes &amp; ſtaues as I were a thefe / to take me &amp; put me in many dyuers paynes and dyſpyteous deth. I fedde &amp; nouryſſhed you .xl. yere in wylderneſſe with delycate manna / &amp; for you cauſed wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter to renne out of the harde ſtone. And ye cauſed me to be fedde with bytter ayſel &amp; gall / &amp; cauſed the blode and water to renne out of my ſyde. I gaue to you lawes by Moyſes accordynge to reaſon / and ye haue cauſed me ayenſt reaſon withoute treſpaſſe to be condempned to cruell deth. I by correccyon of your aduerſaryes ledde you in to the londe of promyſſyon / and put you in to my ſwete &amp; delectable vyneyarde / where often I gaue you the vyctory of your enemyes. And ye not ſatyſfyed with deryſyon &amp; mockynge me with many greuous &amp; cruell paynes that I haue ſuffred / to lede me to torne &amp; all to rente with ſtrokes to put me vpon the croſſe. I haue ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>alted you aboue all other people / &amp; ye haue mocked me &amp; cauſed me to be punyſſhed with ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ers &amp; treſpaſſours what thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge haue I done vnto you / or what vnkyndnes
<pb facs="tcp:812:6"/>haue ye founde in me that ye entreate me ſoo vngently haue not ye founde me mercyfull and gracyous to you in your nedes. I haue choſen you &amp; ye haue refuſed me. I haue brought you forthe and nouryſſhed you as my chyldren / &amp; ye haue deſpyſed me. O how vnryght wyſe and vnkynde theſe rewardes be / to rewarde euyll for good / ſhame &amp; vylany for worſhyp &amp; good and dygnyte malyce and enemyte for fauour and frendſhyp / trouble and vexacyon for peas and tranquyllyte / greuous and bytter payne with aduerſyte for pleaſure &amp; proſperyte / cruell and ſhamefull deth for proſperous lyfe.</p>
            <p>AFter thou haſt with deuocyon beholde our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyd ſauyour &amp; conſydered well his cruell outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyous payne / turne the than towarde his ſorowfull mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der / and beholde well her heuy chere &amp; ſorowfull coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce / and ſe how pyteouſly the teeres renne out of her gracyous eyen and dyſtayne her beauteous vyſage how dolefully ſhe ſobbed / how pyteouſly ſhe wryngeth her hondes with many a ſorowfull ſyghynge comynge from her herte replete with ſorowe and heuynes / how ſhe falleth often in ſwounynge her tender herte lyke to be braſte for pyte &amp; compaſſyon of her chylde that was and is very god &amp; man / how ſhe ſomtyme amonge her ſwounynge and greuous paynes with cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenaunce dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>conſolate / caſteth vp her eyen for pyte and loue vpon her ſwete ſone and bleſſyd chylde / and anone for pyte &amp; moderly compaſſyon ſhe felle downe in ſwounynge in more greuous payne and ſorowe than ſhe was before.</p>
            <p>¶ O good lady moder of pyte noo meruayle thoughe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> were heuy and ſorowfull to ſe thy bleſſyd and mercyfull ſone ſuffre gyltles ſo many greuous paynes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:812:6"/>
            <p>¶ O bleſſyd lady the moder of mercy how ful of ſorowe and anguyſſhe was thy herte / to ſe thy bleſſyd ſone his heed peryſſhed with ſharpe thornes whiche thou were wonte to lappe full tenderly.</p>
            <p>¶ O louely lady quene of heuen and example of honeſte how heuy was thy chere &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenaunce to ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble face of thy bleſſyd chylde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was &amp; is very god &amp; man foyled with the ſpyttynge of rybawdes and caytyues.</p>
            <p>¶ O ſwete lady the floure of chaſtyte / how depe &amp; how ſorowfull were thy ſyghynges to ſe offred bytter ayſell and galle to thy chylde to drynke / to whome thou were wonte to gyue ſwete virgyns mylke of thy bleſſyd breſt</p>
            <p>¶ O gracyous lady the perfyte myrrour of vertue and goodnes / how full of ſorowe were thy ſobbynge to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the Innocent handes and feet of thy bleſſyd childe that neuer dyd treſpaſſe nayled harde to a tree / the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che thou were wonte to dreſſe and waſſhe reuerently.</p>
            <p>¶ O benygne lady welle of mercy and grace / how co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyouſly dyde thyn eyen ſhedde out flodes of bytter tee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / whan thou beheldeſt the blode flowynge out of the hondes and feet of thy dereſone / the whiche thou were wonte to lappe and ſwadell full moderly.</p>
            <p>¶ O gloryous lady the tree of lyfe / how ferefull were thy ſwounynges and how pytefully were thy wryngyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges of thy bleſſyd handes / whan thou beheldeſt the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyd fruyte of thy body all to torne and rente / hangynge deed vpon the croſſe that thou haddeſt brought forth &amp; nouryſſhed tenderly vpon thy lappe.</p>
            <p>¶ O mercyfull lady the moder of pyte and compaſſyon how greuous was thy pyteous &amp; te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der herte wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſwerde of ſorowe &amp; compaſſyon / to ſe a ſpere to ryue his ſyde / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had choſen to dwell within thy bleſſyd ſydes / 
<pb facs="tcp:812:7"/>and made his holy tabernacle not ferre from thy herte.</p>
            <p>¶ O bleſſyd lady I knowe well that thou ſholdeſt haue dyed before hym or with hym yf thou haddeſt not had ſtedfaſt byleue &amp; hope that he ſholde lyue agayne. Here thou mayſt apply thy ſelfe to ſorowe &amp; mourne with thy carefull &amp; heuy lady / for it beſemeth not well that ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous &amp; ſo vertuous a lady waſſhe her face with teeres &amp; thou a kaytyfe &amp; a ſynner departe a ſynner with drye eyen ſyth he ſuffred theſe paynes for loue of the / it is not accordynge that ſo noble &amp; prudent a lady ſobbe / ſyghe and ſwoune for thy lordes deth / and thou that arte ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gecte lyke an vnkynde ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / leue hym without pyte or compaſſyon / ſyth he dyed for the loue of the.</p>
            <p>AFter this y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſt ymagyn &amp; thynke that what tyme the body of our lorde &amp; bleſſyd ſauyour is take downe from the croſſe / our bleſſyd lady haſteth her towarde it with heuy chere / &amp; enbraſeth hym in her ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes &amp; gyueth ſorowfull kyſſynges medled with bytter teres / &amp; that ſhe beholdynge his body &amp; blody woundes wepeth ſo pyteouſly / that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſanguyn teeres medled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>cyous blode renne downe on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deed body in mour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge &amp; ſorowynge the pyteous deth of her dere ſone / ſayth to hym in this wyſe. A my dere ſone my lorde &amp; ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerayne / my ſocour &amp; comforte / my Ioye &amp; my pleaſure &amp; my felycyte / thy ſharpe tourmentes &amp; Innocent deth perceth my herte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſorowe &amp; heuynes &amp; wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth it gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uouſly. O ye vnky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; harde herted people / how might ye for pyte punyſſhe hym that neuer offended / how ye myght fy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in your hertes to bete your ſouerayne may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre that taught you the waye of vertue / how coude ye for pyte ſlee your connynge ſurgyn the whiche heled by
<pb facs="tcp:812:7"/>myracles the blynde / deef / and lame / why wolde ye ſlee your wyſe phyſycyen that gaue lyf to the deed. O ye vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynde ſcourges nayles ſpere and thornes / how durſte ye perſe the fleſſhe of your maker &amp; lorde. O thou ſtron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge &amp; ſturdy tree / for vnkyndnes alſo I may accuſe the / why dydeſt thou not leue &amp; put awaye thy naturall ſtyf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and bowe thy braunches to fauour &amp; eaſe my dere ſone all weryed with ſore payne and tourmentes.</p>
            <p>¶ O how fortunate be ye chaſt virgyns chylderles and honeſt wyues &amp; wydowes alſo / that haue your children to comforte you &amp; gladde you in your ſorowe &amp; dyſeaſe. But alas for ſorowe &amp; pite my bleſſyd ſone that was my Ioye &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte that neuer dyde offende / lyeth before my face ſlayne cauſeles / &amp; I haue no moo. ¶ O holy au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell Gabryell thou ſaluted me with wordes of grete Ioye &amp; gladnes / but now my Ioye &amp; gladnes ben tourned in to grete ſorowe &amp; heuynes. Thou ſaydeſt I ſholde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyue and brynge forth the ſone of god / &amp; that his kyngdom &amp; reygne ſholde euer endure / but beholde now and ſe the bleſſyd fruyte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I conceyued thrugh thy wordes cruelly ſlayne. Thou called me full of grace &amp; ſayd / our lorde was with me / but ſe now how harde grace I fynde in the vnkynde people that hath taken my lorde fro me / &amp; put hym to ſhamefull deth. Thou calleſt me alſo bleſſyd in thy ſalutacyon / but how may I be bleſſyd ſyth my de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſone my lorde / my Ioye &amp; my blyſſe is refte fro me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnkynde people &amp; robbed of his lyf. Beholde coſyn Ely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſabeth how rufully he is arayed / at whoſe preſence thy ſone Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ioyned in thy wombe. ¶ O myn owne dere ſone at thy natyuyte holy au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelles ſonge ſonges of peas myrth &amp; melody. And now agayne thy deth the vngen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll people made a noyſe of grete trouble / ſorowe &amp; heuy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / cryenge
<pb facs="tcp:812:8"/>with malycyous voyces. Crucyfye hym / without ruthe or pyte. At thy byrth alſo kynges of ferre cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees aſſembled togyder &amp; ledde by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> light of a ſterre dyde to the moche worſhyp &amp; reuerence / and now thyn owne neyghbours blynde with hatefull malyce haue ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred them ayenſt the with dyſceyte and falſenes to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dempne the to deth. ¶ O ryghtwyſe Symeon / ſe how he is vnryghtfully ſlayne whome thou deſyreſt ſore to ſe or thou ſholdeſt dye. Now fele I the ſore ſtroke of the ſharpe ſwerde of ſorowe &amp; heuines that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> faydeſt ſholde thryll my herte. Beholde bleſſyd baptyſt how pyteouſly that meke downe is put to deth on whome y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſaweſt the holy ghoſt deſcende whan that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> baptyſed hym in flom Iordan. Beholde how that immaculate lambe lyeth In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nocently ſlayne that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſaydeſt / ſholde take awaye ſynne and wyckednes. ¶ O dere ſone / how ſhall I ceaſe of ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe / there is no remedy but onely in the / therfore bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyd chylde ſyth I am thy moder haue pyte &amp; compaſſyon on me / &amp; other tourne to lyfe agayne or take my lyfe fro me for my ſorowe ſwete ſone I ſe none other remedy.</p>
            <p>¶ The holy ordre of au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelles I beſeche you to helpe me that gloryous aungell that is my keper and counſeyle be in my kepynge as thou thynkeſt mooſt profytable to my ſoule and to preſent my prayer before the throne of the gloryous trynyte. And I thanke the bleſſyd aungell whiche arte my keper to kepe me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may euerlaſtyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loue the and thanke the in the heueuly Cyte.</p>
            <p>¶ The ſeconde ordre of aungelles I beſeche you that I may haue by your prayers &amp; helpe reuelacyon from the trynyte of ſuche thynges as ye wolde I ſholde doo his pleaſure / and with aſſyſtence of his grace to do them.</p>
            <p>¶ The thyrde ordre of pryncypates I beſeche you ſo to
<pb facs="tcp:812:8"/>helpe thy prelates &amp; prynces in gouernynge of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that they may lyue in reſte / &amp; truly ſerue theyr lorde god / &amp; that at the houre of deth ye be preſent to delyuer our ſoules from daunger of the deuyll / and brynge vs to the endleſſe Ioye of the celeſtyall paradyſe.</p>
            <p>¶ The fourthe ordre of poteſtates I beſeche you to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe my ghoſtly enemyes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they neuer <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>uayle to hurte me bodyly ne ghoſtly / &amp; to delyuer me fro y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fals cautels by the whiche they entende the deſtruccyon of my ſoule.</p>
            <p>¶ The fyfth ordre of vertues I beſeche you for to praye that I may haue ſtrength in body &amp; ſoule to execute the werkes of that vertue &amp; that my memory &amp; reaſon may be more apte to receyue &amp; vnderſtande by your helpe &amp; prayer. Alſo the gyftes of nature be made more parfyte to the vſe &amp; vertue &amp; to the pleaſure of my lorde god.</p>
            <p>¶ The ſyxth ordre of domynacyon I beſeche you that by youre helpe and prayer that my ſoule may haue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte domynacyon vpon my body / to rule it accordynge to reaſon and to the wyll of my lorde god / and that I may haue vyctory in temptacyon of myn enemye / and parfyte pacyence in all trybulacyons.</p>
            <p>¶ The .vii. ordre of thrones I beſeche you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by your hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe &amp; prayer I may execute the werkes of mercy the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che perteyneth to the ryghtwyſneſſe of god &amp; of my ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghbour / &amp; at the houre of deth whan I ſhall receyue Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gement for the dedes of my lyfe / that by the merytes of you I may fynde my lorde god my mercyfull Iuge.</p>
            <p>¶ The .viii. ordre of cheruphyn I beſeche you praye my lorde god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may haue the gyfte of wyſdome to knowe the goodnes of my lorde god &amp; kyndnes whiche he hath ſhewed me. And to knowe tho thynges whiche be to his pleaſure and that I may do them / &amp; tho thynges that be
<pb facs="tcp:812:9"/>to his dyſpleaſure that I may haue grace to fele them.</p>
            <p>¶ The .ix. ordre of ſeraphyns I beſeche you to praye for me that I may haue the gyfte of feruent loue in my lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de god / and the ſwetnes of deuocion in his ſeruyce with holy meditacyon / that my ſoule be enflambed with loue of the gloryous trynyte / and endles Ioye of his mooſt bleſſyd preſence. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>¶ Here endeth a medytacyon of the .vii. ſhedynges of the blode of our lorde Iheſu cryſte.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Enprynted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don in Fleteſtrete at the ſygne of the ſonne / by wynkyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de worde. <date>The yere of our lorde god. M. ccccc. ix.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="printers_device">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Wynkyn .de. Worde.</head>
                  <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:812:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
